let me ask you a couple of things that
have occurred to me in terms of not what
we're going to talk about but you know
like the ground rules if you like for
want of a better word you know things
like for example I mean what I don't
really have a sort of clear picture in
my mind which is maybe no bad thing
given what it is we're attempting to do
here right not to have to clear up in
the mind all right
that may be part of the problem right I
mean did you see a sort of picking a
topic or a problem or whatever and
centering a discussion around there or
just kind of talking to each other about
some of the I'd and see where it goes
kind of things see what it evolves into
or what do you have in mind I think I
kind of at least at first for this one
just sort of had in mind like you know
sort of just what jumped out at you you
know and like what are were some of the
concepts what do they relate to you know
in your experience up to this point and
just kind of have that I just gather its
own you know energy or whatever and then
if we want to later on you know we can
pick out specific topics and you know
try and apply it well I mean the way I
see it we're complete noobs at this
right so I mean we're seeing out what
this whole thing of coherence is all
about you know what I mean I mean I I
don't know what personal experiences you
may or may not have had of dropping into
coherence with people in the past I'm
not sure I've really got any benchmarks
at all in terms of my own experience not
of really having consciously
deliberately achieved you know any any
kind of coherence in a group so you know
I'm I'm a complete virgin really and so
for for me at least this is about
feeling out what it is what you know guy
just just to get some sense of it really
that's that's kind of where I'm at
yeah and I mean you know this would be
where Matt would probably be a really
good input because I mean that's kind of
I mean that's essentially what he does
up there you know
besides being you know the teacher that
he is so he has sort of a broadcast
system there with him being the teacher
but they also do a whole out of what we
would
all inquiry you know which I don't know
if you've listened you watched any of
the you know they have the video from
the summit public consumption I haven't
watched the members fully fully expect I
have access to the members area I
haven't watched a full on I've only
watched the whatever it was an hour and
eight minutes one so one of the one of
the facilitator guys in that video
talked about our inquiry and I mean you
know I think that is I mean I have a
fair amount of experience with just kind
of being in that space and so I mean to
me a lot of what coherent seems to be
about is about being able to embody that
kind of space where you're you know
you're not coming at it with your you
know your baggage or your fullness that
they talked about in that video isn't it
yeah coming from it from a place of
fullness not a place of need yes yes and
so that also goes to this whole anti
rival risks you know concept that is
talked about a lot where we're not
really in a you know we don't want to
come to any of these discussions with
with rivalry strategies you know
whatever yeah yeah sure and really like
that's the whole idea is that if we can
hold that space and embody that you know
dynamic together then you know that's
really the only way anything you know
interesting or creative is gonna emerge
because otherwise we're just kind of
holding it down and playing game a
essentially yeah I mean that's one of
the things that Jordan mentioned wasn't
it is the danger of thinking you're
playing game B whereas actually you're
just playing another version of game a
right right let me see there's now I'm
gonna get my notes out here there was
something in there that I mean you know
and again we can just sort of take this
and run with it at this point cuz I mean
you know if Mac is able to join us
that's great otherwise you know we can
always just crack on it's a that comes
along and if Ben comes along and great
but they're already what they're six
minutes late I don't think we should be
holding our breath for them
right so let's see so at some point
they're talking and Jordan has this riff
about let's see the least okay so he's
talking about urgency and responsibility
and he's talking about how to properly
respond to urgent C and it there's this
theme that goes back a little bit in the
conversation about having patience and
humility right and so he's talking about
how like he gives the analogy of James
Bond you know when he's like the stakes
are high and the urgency is super high
but he can't you know give any of that
off or else it'll ruin the whole you
know plan so the idea he said that
really jumped out at me was something
like the least bit of feeling the
urgency right so you're aware of it you
understand
the ambience I'm getting quote you're
not getting nervous from it or whatever
you're not getting right yeah not
getting tightened up from it yeah yeah
that's right and so what happens when
you get caught in that right is that you
know guarantees failure by suggesting
one of two strategies that you either
move into something that's not yet
possible in coherence so that's sort of
like you know trying to move too fast
right into something that you know maybe
maybe just between the two of us like
that would be an example of like me
trying to push forward with a different
set of definitions say than what you
have right we must do something this is
something therefore we must do it yeah
right well even though we haven't even
let's say establish basic ground rules
or you know we're operating on two
different definitions you know something
well yeah and actually that's something
else that I was thinking about in the
round so this was exactly that
definitions I mean we're likely to get
into conversations where we're using
terms which holds different meanings for
different people right and so the need
to define those terms during the course
of the conversation as they come up you
know what I mean I mean we need to be
ready any individual needs to be ready
to say okay hang on what exactly do you
mean by that you know because there's a
lot of words like that especially when
you enter into mythology really
politics ideology you know what I mean
you know people have completely
different meanings it's a completely
different baggage that they bring to
these terms you know this really needs
to be ironed out right yeah that's right
I mean especially like you said when you
get into you know really complex topics
and metaphysics and you know whatever
else I mean and even in even in things
that are more concrete like say
government or something I mean you still
need to have a common set of terms that
you're gonna use and you need to make
sure that's established so that would be
something like trying to push forward
too quickly into something that you know
is not gonna operate with incoherence
and then you could also the second thing
that you know the second danger you run
into when you get caught up in the
feeling of the urgency is you're gonna
try it you might try and rationalize
pulling from the game a toolkit which is
like what I think you were saying
earlier about you know playing game a or
utilizing game a strategies without even
really realizing it yeah well I mean and
it's gonna be you know with the best
will in the world and I mean Jordan
Jordan and Daniel have got to be further
along the road than most on this right
he's the first to admit that thousands
and thousands of times you know that he
has fucked up one way or another you
know so as the expectation needs to be
that that we're gonna fuck up a lot you
know what I mean and therefore watch
yeah and and that it's hard especially
coming from you know this is another
thing is what we're running game a code
right we've always run game a code and
not run game a code is extremely
difficult even when you have this is
what Jamie was talking about right even
when people have at the boom fest or
with the mushrooms among their friends
when they have that experience they drop
into coherence they drop into flow they
conceptualize it using game a code right
and and then so straightaway becomes
part of game a it's not Gabey it becomes
straightaway part of game eight and it's
incredibly hard not to do that I mean I
don't know how we go about not doing
that we're gonna have to be constantly
checking up on both ourselves and each
other that we're not doing that right
right which there goes back to this
other point that I was really honing in
on which is like
so Jordan has another riff about like I
call it something like authenticity
detection yeah right and so we have a
end and we all do this like you could
you know you can sniff out somebody
who's not really you know trying to work
something out authentically or you know
or just operating from a script yeah and
then you you know you you have to be you
have to be willing to call bullshit on
somebody else right they have to be
willing to accept that yeah yeah yeah
you're right sorry man you're right I
was doing that yeah that's the thing so
you have to be willing to bullshit but
you also have to be willing to have
somebody else call bullshit on you
absolutely right and that's not easy
either I think I said that to you in a
message didn't either the aspiration to
play game be when we are so entrenched
in game a I think I think is a it's a
lofty one maybe a slightly unrealistic
one but then it's yeah what choice do we
have other toilets do we have yeah
exactly you know and so that I tend to
kind of you know gravitate toward
Jamie's perspective because to me the
biggest concern is like okay how are we
to operate within game B parameters
while still being able to operate in
game a because I mean like you know we
have to correct it and actually game B
is really I mean I don't know maybe you
disagree with this but game being sort
of super to game a but game a strategies
would still be employed to implement
those things which came out of the
playing of game B right I mean there's
still nitty-gritty administrative boring
mechanical stuff that needs doing at the
other end right and that's game a I
would think that that doesn't entirely
go away
you know it's kind of like light and so
what we you know why would the kind of
language that I would use is like we're
holding this space open and you know to
use sager gifs terminology it would be
something like the space between yes and
no so you're like so you're not
committed one way or the other yet
because you're you're waiting you know
you're being patient you're waiting for
something to arise in the space between
right but at some point you know we we
have to collapse the wave form you know
what I mean and actually use something
so yes I would say saying again doesn't
it whether that takes ten minutes or
whether that takes ten months doesn't
really matter the the you know when it
happens it happens and everyone will
recognize the fact that it's happened
right I mean the little
there'd be some kind of resonance that
runs through everyone in everyone
involved at the same time ha ha ha ha
hang on we're onto something here right
and everyone will feel that because
they've all been contributing up until
that point right they've all been
holding whatever parts of it up until
that point and then when it all
crystallizes together into in turn into
that thing into the third that that I
mean I again I'm talking from a place of
no experience but I suspect that
recognition will occur at that moment
right well I think that's what the I
mean that's what in a lot of ways that's
what rule Omega is about is is so
coherence is about the recognition right
all right I mean so the more the more we
communicate and the more we leave the
space open and like you said no matter
how long it takes and all along the way
there's gonna be little moments of
recognition and stuff but that's
basically the process of building
coherence at least that's the way it
seems to me ya know it's a partly
intellectual or cognitive thing but it's
also largely intuitive right you gotta
you gotta let go of the linear logical
thought process to a certain degree and
allow the more mysterious things to
happen
yeah and you know like in the very
beginning there was a nice you know
summary of kind of what game a is and
has been and a lot of that is totally
related to denotative language right
does that make sense
yeah well he called semantic language
rather than correct language yeah yeah
and so it's like if you can put it into
words
you know it's sort of like the Dow or
something right like the Dow that you
can point to you is not the Dow or what
every much I'm on board with that idea
but equally you can I really like that
idea of using language as a thing not to
describe a thing but to awaken in the
person hearing the words pointing them
to an experience in themselves which
they can recognize yeah that's that
language that it's not yeah not
describing a thing but now I mean the
thing we have to be the piece of art the
same feeling that the artists themselves
held in their hearts when they were
creating the piece of art you know what
I mean and so it's yeah it's
communicating and so yeah that's so I've
forgotten what exactly my point was but
that's well I mean we have to be able to
you know remind ourselves constantly
that you know words or pointers I mean
like language is pointer it's kind of
it's the same thing as like the Maps not
the territory yeah yeah absolutely
absolutely it's exactly like that I like
that's a great analogy yeah but you were
saying about like so we were talking
about the these peak experiences let's
say and if we're working on coherence
and we build up to a point where we
reach you know a place of recognition
and something new or interesting it
rises you know we also have to be able
to kind of let that like at some point
that's gonna have to unspool and unravel
because to me it just seems like you
can't get around that like what we were
talking about how at some point you got
to go you know pay some bills can I just
stop you just on just on a clarity thing
so what do you mean by spool and unravel
do you mean needs to be articulated then
in
in actual you know semantics language or
do you mean it falls apart no I mean it
well it can oh I was meaning it can fall
apart right and and you have to be kind
of okay with that
yeah I think Jamie said something in
there about he was talking about having
patience and like to me it sounded like
a lot like what happens when you're in
on psychedelics right so it's like you
sort of unravel the ego you know to a
certain point and when you're like when
you're in the peak I mean often times
there's just no sense of self whatsoever
and then that's that then has to be
rebuilt through that experience and so
it's kind of like when we reach these
points of coherence it's not necessarily
that the key is to maintain that but the
key is to be patient enough to allow it
to unravel and take new forms right so
I'm not saying that very articulately
but it's a help to getting back there
again once you've been there and would
you would you say that's the case that
the more you get there the easier it is
to get there or not I would well I don't
know how I don't know how much
expectations which block you're getting
there again it could also be well it
could but see that's a that's a game a
thing yeah right to think that it's
always got to be the same way now you
know I would I would say that you get
better at it I do think it's a skill you
know and I think they they talk about
that in fact there's something that you
know going back to the thing about being
able to you know call like you're just
not allowed to let people you know play
game a hey I'm unnecessarily kind of
right and so there's like skillful
discernment yeah so it is a skill to be
able to say and to do it with tact and
to do it in a way that's constructive to
say hey look you're in your bullshit you
know you're not you're not
connecting right now you're you know and
and I don't know find ways to work
around that I guess but I mean there's
another video that Jamie you know did
something maybe it's scaling coherence
or something but he was talking about
those meetings that he went to and how
easily you know things got derailed by
topics that just weren't even relative
relevant to what they were trying to
solve you know and just all those old
game a feelings come rushing up and the
whole thing falls apart yeah right and
so I mean to some extent you have to be
willing to be patient but I mean there's
also I mean there's a point when I mean
I think you're not allowed to let
somebody get away with it you know in
certain environments necessary there's a
purity of intention and there's a purity
of passing on Jeff Jordan talks about
this in another video it parts passing
on in a high-fidelity manner that which
comes to you you know what I mean and so
you know if you're bringing a piece of
information from another source and it
needs to be done not so I'm gonna find
quite the right words here but as
truthfully as possible you know not
leaving a little bit of it out because
it doesn't fit with what you said before
and therefore might not make you look
good or whatever you know that
everything has to be passed on high
fidelity screening out noise from
signals you remember all of this noise
from signal thing oh yeah and so does
this what you were talking about the
discernment of noise from signal not
intentionally adding noise to your
signals you know I mean that's crucially
awesome right or even or even on you
know with without you know unconsciously
that's why we need each other yeah yeah
yeah right because I don't know you know
we've all got our traumas and bullshit
and we've all got our stories that we
tell ourselves you know and we really
need others to point those things out or
help us you know understand that we need
to suspend them for a little oh yeah
yeah or at least we need to hold them
lightly I would
yeah you know and the so the thing that
you da man now I've lost what you were
just saying we're talking about fidelity
and about reducing noise and creating
more signals so there's a there's a
thing at the end there about you know I
think he uses the word ideology but you
know it could be just as well you know
worldview or paradigm that you know all
all ideologies have some degree of noise
and some degree of signal and by
definition the paradigm or the worldview
is is a you know a condensed version of
reality like it just you you can't
possibly get all of it you know in there
and so there's bound to be noise and
bound to be signal and so the idea is
the more we can sort of connect and
cohere the more hopefully we can reduce
the noise and increase the signal would
you say what is noise in one situation
could be signal in a different situation
yeah I I think that's probably true you
know I look at worldviews and paradigms
like I mean where we want to be is in a
place where we can differentially apply
paradigms depending on the situation
yeah you know because one map doesn't
apply to every you know place you're you
find yourself not necessarily because
they're dictionary meaning but for me
personally and this is my own thing but
an ideology is something which you stick
to even in the face of significant
evidence to the contrary whereas a
paradigm is not necessarily thus right a
paradigm is a bit more in my mind anyway
not everyone might have this meaning but
in my mind a paradigm is a bit more of a
scientific concept in that in the face
of overwhelming evidence to the contrary
you're happy to drop it whereas an
ideology well but there's more of an
emotional attachment ideal as you write
right right yeah I mean I think that's
accurate you know you could say a
paradigm can shift into an ideology
it's not held lightly enough yeah yeah
and that's it and then the static
institutions grow up around it and
that's that that's when you know a
paradigm has become an ideology when you
have static institutions which despite
the fact they no longer relevant no
longer serve a useful function they're
still there doing their thing right
because they have you know they have an
interest of their own yeah they had a
use in the past they came into existence
for a very good reason but that use is
no longer that you know that they use is
no longer really relevant but there they
are there they are because their
institution oh yeah I mean I think
that's that's maybe not a bad way of
differentiating between a paradigm in an
ideology is does it have institutions
built up around it well yeah but I mean
you could still hold you know something
that you know somebody else might have
as an ideology you know you could still
employ that you know I don't know that's
that's tricky because there's this other
argument I've been having over there
with our discussion with the guy Derek
BG yeah yeah you know and it's like well
that's a tricky deal because you can you
can convince yourself that you're not
really attached to the ideology and yet
you know you can you really are I mean
that's the whole green performative
contradiction is that you know to say
that all all things are true or equally
true and yet mine is the most true it's
sort of like like there is Jordan
Peterson says right is that you know
what you believe is not necessary to got
anything to do with what you think of
what you say is what you do it's how you
live you know what I mean that this is
the best this is the best indicator of
what you actually believe and I think
there's a great deal of truth to that
what was the other thing is the last
thing you said Miranda knew something
anyway whatever doesn't matter that was
the that was that was the important one
and I think that I think that's
absolutely right you all right yeah I
think you what you were saying about an
ideology even though you think you may
not be bound by if you live according to
it then you are indeed bound by it right
and
and the evidence is right there right
and if you can't you know if you can't
take a criticism of it for example you
know another good one absolutely yeah
absolutely so there was one thing that
popped out of the video at me I was okay
I was I thought this is gonna be a quite
interesting topic for discussions
remember we mentioned the four-minute
mile thing well somebody did the
four-minute mile now ever since then
everybody's been doing four-minute miles
now high school high school kids can do
four-minute miles do you remember that
little bit yeah so let me ask what you
what you think about this do you think
that it's as simple as once it's done by
someone and people know it can be done
then you know it's just a kind of
confidence thing right oh well someone
else did it therefore it's possible
therefore I have a chance of doing it do
you think it's as simple as that
or do you think it's something more
profound and speaking to a sort of
another layer of organization in the
universe something along the line of
Rupert Sheldrake's morphic resonance
where he says that you know once a
substance is crystallized once somewhere
in the world in one lab somewhere in the
world in other labs elsewhere in the
world it crystallizes more easily
because somewhere in the universe is an
imprint of the fact that that has been
done now right and so there's a there's
a template for it if you like and so
it's more easily accomplished in the
future so well what do you think of
those two ideas in the explanation of
why the four-minute mile once it was
done once was done a billion times
afterwards you know I would say there's
probably some truth in both of them I
know that's sort of a cop-out but I mean
I do think that there has to be
something to the first idea because
there may you know take not even the
four-minute mile take something that's
just never been done at all before you
know just the fact that somebody else
somebody did it and now it's a thing
makes it more likely that somebody else
is gonna pick up on it and do it it was
what the quality in ice skating wasn't
it the for the for the for turn jump in
ice skate had done and then once it was
done once every one includes it in their
routine well and so it's so it may just
be as simple as the fact that you know
well some of it could be technologically
driven you know like say with an athlete
it could be some
thing about the equipment you know that
they're using you know the morphic
resonance thing is really interesting I
don't really know where I fall on that
have you have you come across the idea
before you familiar with Rupert children
ah somewhat I mean I'm familiar with it
or vaguely but not you know not in any
great detail I love it I think it's a
great idea for on a variety of levels
are for example the DNA of a and we were
one of the things that came up in that
Joe Rogan podcast you guys are talking
about was was ant colonies right yeah
yeah you know the layout and design for
an ant colony is not there in an
individual ants DNA right somehow or
other in the collaboration in the
relationships between those ants the
design emerges from that right it's it's
very much an emergent thing from the
design for collaboration so there's the
individuals and there's the
relationships between those individuals
and that whole mess out back to the
coherence thing right it's a form of
coherence in the ends right the colony
emerges out of that and so his idea is
that somewhere in a place that we don't
yet understand a little energy frequency
or whatever that we that we haven't yet
that we haven't yet tapped into in the
same way that stone men would have had
no idea if there was radio signals
passing over their heads right there and
then no concept or in exactly the same
way there is this energy field of yet
yet we have two of which we as yet have
no knowledge which has you know
templates like the immune system once
you've been exposed to a disease once
somewhere in your immune system is an
imprint of that you get exposed to it
again it's ready to be rolled out
straightaway same sort of principle as
that is that do you think related to you
know young in in a way like the whole
collective unconscious kind of thing
absolutely I think that's related yeah
yeah I do yeah I mean I feel because I
was are you unconscious yeah my read of
the collective unconscious is is also
not so much metaphysical as much as you
know I mean it just it's it is part
the DNA almost I mean it's like us it's
a it's an inherited collection of you
know archetypes that have born
themselves out over time you think
that's contained within each individual
do you think it's contained in the
universe at large and we somehow tuned
into it as individuals no I think we
create it over time so you think it's a
big out there I think we pass it on I
think it probably is within each
individual right but it's not a I don't
know it's a human experience resides in
some way I'm not asking you to explain
the mechanism but resides in some way
within each individual it's not it's not
she is I think it's by the individual
but resides within I think it plays
itself out within the individual yes so
I mean from a certain sense it's like
we're all working on it together like we
obviously share it but in the end it's
something that plays out in the
individual psyche
you know when the rubber hits the road I
mean I don't think it's like I don't
think it's like this other thing that we
you know tap into right we carry it
around okay and pass it on you know what
I mean so it is okay okay that's the way
it's a morphic resonance I do that the
body plan for example in humans you know
heart cells no has to become hard you
know some cells know to become a heart
cells other cells now to become a brain
cells and the ones in the right places
and the body do the right thing and they
all connect together in in in the right
way and and you know this fantastically
complicated design just kind of
assembles itself now again there is not
contained in the DNA the body plan is
not contained in the DNA right the
potential to do all of the jobs and each
and every cell does the making of the
protein so on there is all in there but
the the meta thing is not is not
contained in that so again is morphic
resonance idea explains that that
there's a stamp if you like you know but
I mean I'm not sure I can I I'm not sure
I'm doing a very
good job of creating a picture of this
but you know the human being at the
moment of coming into existence is
stamped by this morphic resonance filled
with the body plan of what it is to be a
human being you know what I mean along
with perhaps the collective unconscious
as it exists up until that moment kind
of thing maybe I thought that possibly
also yeah and so the so the morphic
resonance would be an attempt to answer
the question how does you know a cell
know what to do when it's you know in
the embryonic stage yeah right
you just got this ball of
undifferentiated stem cells and you know
they're dividing rapidly and somehow or
other this one knows to turn into the
liver and this one knows to turn your
brain yeah it's very sequential and if
it gets out of order you're all fuck
it's a fucking mess right and so some
you know there's a plan there's a code
for all of this somewhere or other
there's a and so why is it that that's
not in the DNA I'm curious if there is
the mechanism by which that is
translated is as yet unknown so I'm
sorry I the mechanism by which is
translated if it is in there is not
understood let's put it that way right
right yes 20 trillion cells or something
in the human body and god knows how many
hundreds of different types of cells
there are and you know they're dying and
coming into existence all the time all
the time tens of millions of them a day
you know and yeah it all just obviously
happens without our awareness but
there's got to be some kind of a
template some kind of a blueprint that
this happens according to right see you
want there to be like almost like a
world of forms or something from which
all these thoughts on a card in well the
reflection the I guess yeah I guess
there's certainly certainly relation I
don't know that I want it I'm just
saying that I know I really like the
idea of morphing it's it resonates with
me if you know sometimes you hear ideas
and they just yeah yeah yeah man I love
that that really that feels right
doesn't mean it's right of course but it
just it just feels right and that's it's
one of those ideas it just feels it
explains a lot of mysterious things it
doesn't really explain it because
there's no mechanism there's no you know
here it is this is I can show it to you
there's no there's nothing like that but
but nevertheless it explains a lot it's
a bit like terence mckenna's hypothesis
about the
evolution of the consciousness of
mankind being brought about by the fact
that a lot of monkeys ate a lot of
hallucinogenic plants right yeah right
it's they an ape no way of proving this
but it makes a lot of fucking sense
right yeah for sure yeah I love that
idea you know the thing about the likes
so things like morphic resonance to me
it's like okay that gives you a set of
terms and ideas to use to describe
something right that really can't be
described in a certain sense now it may
be that Rupert Sheldrake thinks that you
know there's something really like real
there and I don't know I mean maybe and
there may well be but it's certainly
useful to think about and I like the
idea of resonance you know because
that's sort of I mean we're all sort of
operating at a certain you know
frequency and and what we're doing is
and coherence is a lot about resonating
right harmonizing those frequencies
isn't it's about finding and finding a
harmony not necessarily homogenizing
them but but but stacking them in a new
novel and complex way which creates a
hitherto unknown harmony I think that's
that's right
kind of what it's about right I would
say that's true yeah I'm told Rupert
Sheldrake he's been somewhat vilified by
the scientific community because he's
pretty out there but he's my opinion
he's a true scientist in the sense that
you know he he comes up with reasonable
explanations for phenomena and puts them
forward as hypotheses and that's
entirely reasonable right he's not
offering them as theories he's offering
them as hypotheses and he questions
where the science has become somewhat
doctrinal over the last few decades you
know and questions the validity of a
huge number of the papers that are put
out there is self referencing self
peer-reviewed papers you know that have
no real they they're just out there in
order to create firstly money for the
publishing companies but also a bill
an ability to give people masters and
PhDs you know what I mean so a lot of
these published stuff is kind of just to
put people through masters and PhD
courses that I get the accreditation you
know so as a consequence of these
criticisms not to mention the fact that
he questions whether constants are
really constant there seem to be changes
in the value of the gravitational
constant the speed of light you know
what I mean he seems to have things yeah
in to have fluctuated over time and if
that is true would require a complete
re-evaluation of our whole notion of
what what constant what it means for a
constant to be a constant right now
the entire universe is in some kind of
state of flux where the speed of light
is not always the same the gravitational
constant is not always say a mass and
energy content at the universe is not
always the same you know that if if that
were true and I'm not saying it is but
it's a reasonable question to ask
because at the end of the day these
things are assumptions right though then
there is no way of demonstrating beyond
a reasonable doubt that the total mass
and energy in the universe never changes
right we've never seen a change in any
closed system but that does not mean
necessarily that there is an energy
being created and destroyed perhaps in
equal quantities all the time in the
universe you know me but it doesn't mean
that there isn't energy being created
and destroyed in the universe right well
see that really resonates with my whole
you know idea or just the perception
that you know we're kind of we're in a
dialectic with whatever you want to call
God you know and so the whole thing is
like we're co-creating you know the
thing on the fly essentially and so this
idea that these constants would
fluctuate is is right in line with that
because you know and we're we're really
interesting because we've come in and
with all the technology and stuff like
we've changed a lot of the parameters in
ways that you know no other living thing
has up to this point and so in a lot of
ways you know that's that's playing god
I guess in a sense but
you know the fact that we're now in this
kind of feedback loop where we're
actually changing or setting the
parameters within which we operate is
it's quite amazing and scary
have we not always done that is it just
that no our power to do so is increasing
exponentially now is I think I think
it's I think the technology you know
that a lot that makes that happen is so
much more powerful now and it's oh and
it's and it's on an exponential curve at
the moment I mean you know it seems to
be anyway I don't know if that's you
talked about this dozen years that we've
got a toolkit which you know has
developed over millions and millions and
millions of years and we've got an
environment we developed over of a
couple of centuries really decades if
you want depending on how you look at it
but whatever and you know it's just
random chance some of our toolkit works
pretty well
all those are completely not fit for
purpose right it's just let's just sit
and that's pretty random which work and
which don't that that's all pretty
random and so yeah that's intense the
need for a game B right I mean that's
okay be right and yeah exactly exactly
and although it's not a accelerate
I mean seriously at going back to
Terence Mckenna he thinks that the whole
thing is on an exponential curve time
itself he reckons is speeding up because
as time goes on and things become more
complex and more normal in any given
unit of time there's more going on which
means that time is going faster right
there's more events occurring within
that time he defines time as the space
between events right and so if you have
events and well you're compressing time
basically and so time is speeding up
exponentially which means evolution is
speeding up exponentially and I mean it
gives a pretty obvious example you know
you've got hundreds of thousands of
years of you know or millions of years
of your various pre Homo sapiens to homo
sapiens and then you've got you know
maybe a few hundred thousand years to
aggregate to tools and so on then you've
got a few tens of thousands of years to
agriculture and then a couple of
millennia to industrial and then a
couple of centuries to information you
know what I mean in this whole there's
the the whole thing is just just on that
on an X
thing yeah so then what happens when you
run up against the like biological
reality that you know bodies just don't
change that fast that's exactly where we
are now isn't it that's exactly what we
run up against right now is exactly that
is exactly that it's like we're reaching
some kind of critical you know mass or
something think sorry gone no no it's
just like we're reaching some kind of
critical point in that curve you know
where the two things are sort of
crossing each other kind of up until
relatively recently technology has been
primarily about assisting the biology
right so it's washing machines and
refrigerators and cars and roads and
transportation systems and running water
and electricity and all of these kinds
of things which for the organism itself
right the biological organism these were
all good things for the biological
organism itself and so adaptation of the
biological organism not really required
until relatively recently when
technology has started to take on a form
which is no longer just about assisting
the biological organism it's gone beyond
that right it's gone into realms which
is way beyond the biological nature of
the organism which is why of course the
biology is now running into conflict
would you would you agree with that
analysis that sound reasonable to you
yeah so you're saying well I mean I
don't know the so cars let's see so
let's run it back the up until a certain
point technology was really there to
assist biology yeah the needs of the
biological organism yeah well comfort
you know right but I mean I don't know
that transportation maybe in
transportation was maybe not the best
example but certainly medicine and yes
and electricity and machinery and you
know being able to increase production
of food increased production of goods
you know all of it all of this kind of
people saying Isis you know all of these
sorts of things is reducing the amount
of danger the amount of time the amount
of effort that goes into yeah yeah I
mean I don't know it just pops into my
head but I delayed yeah so then when
that so then you run that up to a point
where it's no longer really serving the
interest of the organism I mean I yeah
not the needs of the boil not the needs
of the biology right so you know the
Internet the mobile phone network the I
don't know the extended working days the
I don't know I'm trying to think of
other examples but you know internet and
Mobile's is the motto of our most of
disease and most transformations right
and I mean the thing about it the thing
about all of that ends up being that you
know like especially if you look at
something like social media that you
know really does not serve the interests
of the organism because I just don't
know that we're really capable of you
know having meaningful discussion in
groups of that size well the problem
with the social media I mean this is
well documented but the problems of
social media is this echo chamber thing
right is that he tends to gravitate
towards those who think the same as you
do and then and so you never really have
any interesting discussions I mean I
think you and I could probably be
accused of that we're obviously broadly
on the same page in terms of how we see
things and you know that we're it's
right well so you have you have to you
have to you have really like two issues
with that like on the one hand I think
just the fact that we're in you know the
fact that you can find echo chambers is
one problem right and and I'm certainly
guilty of that you know I try to step
outside of that on purpose because I'm
at least aware that that's a problem or
it can be a problem right but then you
also have the issue of just trying to
get together with that many people and
come to a consensus you know I mean this
is not you know there's Dunbar's number
and all of these things about you know
how many people can you really go here
with and so some pretty fucking big
arguments about stuff I'm quite sure
they did but it was easier for them to
come to a consensus you know because it
was us just a smaller number of people I
think even more importantly than the
consensus is the fact that everyone
feels that they have had a chance to
hear have their voice heard in the
process as it played out right and
in 2000 sends a thousands millions that
every individual has no chance of having
their voice heard groups need you know
groups inevitably going to form within
that larger group and representatives of
those groups are now the ones that need
to have the discussions with each other
we're right in the whole identity group
thing because not every member of a
group feels the same way about
everything blah blah blah but then you
layer on top of that you know this sort
of like global corporate financial you
know system and the military-industrial
complex but I mean like these things
then run amok you know with the and and
D let's see what's the word
you know disenfranchised individuals
even more and make individuals feel less
powerful less you know agency less
ownership and what's going on you know
and that's a bad spot to be in by the
fact that the u.s. electorate saw fit to
choose Donald Trump you know not only in
the primaries but then in the general
election as well not that Hillary was
much of a thing but you know that was
the most awful you're an American
citizen right so I mean obviously you
got your right in the thick of it I mean
it was the most even for an outsider it
was the most awful horrible election to
watch because you know everybody hated
both candidates basically so I saw make
a really good point I mean it's obvious
when you hear it but but I'd never
really thought about it in those terms
at the the main reason that Trump won
the election was because he was a
Republican candidate you know it's as
simple as that it's got nothing to do
with Trump with Trump himself but he was
the Republican nominee and Republicans
were in the majority of presidencies and
this as simple as fucking they're well
yeah I don't know I have a slightly
different read on that but you know the
there's so my line on all of that is
there's a round about the 70s the late
70s you know coming out of well actually
I mean you can take it all the way back
to World War two and or the even the
depression and FDR and so there was
really a progressive
politics you know in the Democratic
Party and in this in the States really
in general and then you carry that on
into world war two and a lot of those
people really fought for those
progressive values that FDR stood for
right and then you move that into the
50s and 60s and then you have all this
unrest in the 60s right socially and
they're fighting a culture war at that
point and so then somewhere like in the
it's really with Carter I want to say
you know and and going into Reagan
obviously like there gets this kind of
this financial arrangement between
essentially center right and center left
and this new kind of what we call now I
mean what I would call the neoliberal
project right and I mean I guess Tony
Blair was huge in you know the Third Way
politics and that whole thing is go I
mean that's decades of this sort of idea
you know that we can sort of toe the
line and and work together and for
decades it's just benefited you know
people with money and influence and it's
disenfranchised a whole bunch of people
on the left and right frankly this has
been a quite deliberate strategy by the
by the rich people oh sure they've been
doing for centuries and centuries you
know and at the whole absolutely
democracy thing was just the latest
accommodation that they made in order to
actually even though it looked like
people have more individual liberty
actually it was just a more subtle veil
placed on the control mechanisms that
always existed sure but I mean
government has functioned in in
progressive ways in the past you know it
just it doesn't ever seem to hold
because you know the capitalists just
find a new way to you know make more you
know to wedge in and and you know crowd
out the competitors and all of that sort
of thing but you know my read on trunk
was that this is just
it's finally a you know a full-on you
know that's a populist reaction to
basically a corporatist strategy that's
been going on for decades yeah it's also
I mean I think Russell Brand hit the
nail on the head we said it's no longer
possible with Trump in office it's no
longer possible to look at the political
system and think it's okay yeah to think
that it works to think that it functions
in any even most rudimentary way if it
can produce that you know what I mean
then then then it's it's it's broken
it's fundamentally and profoundly and
irredeemably broken okay so let's take
so then let's take this political
conversation and let's try to
conceptualize like what what game B has
to bring to the table and how you know D
do you see a way that game B can I do
actually sort of interject itself into
that conversation no no not at all but
just as you were just as he was saying
we need to find a way to bring game B to
bear on this problem as you were saying
there something pops into my head which
is not a new idea and it's not the first
time I've had this I'm not first time I
think it fits here's is all I'm saying
is the idea of decentralization though I
think for a long time the state has
become more and more and more unwieldy
you know what I mean and and more and
more decisions are made in a central way
for everybody to go along with and III I
think the game be absolutely has a role
to play in a more decentralized approach
to power and wealth and resource
distribution or I mean decisions being
made at a more local level because it is
so hard to scale game B you know even
across hundreds let alone millions you
know what I mean it seems to me to make
a lot of sense you're trying to play
game B it seems to me to make a lot of
sense of devolve decision-making down to
group size is where game B can sensibly
be played you know what I mean I do you
know that's related in a certain sense
to the transition between you know what
Jordan calls the blue church and the
broadcast model you know into this
where we are now which is kind of a
decentralized you know means of you know
sense-making yeah but that is as we've
already taught is the camps that it
creates right you know I don't actually
think it's improved sense I mean it
didn't print access to sense making but
I don't think it's improved actual this
making of sense by people because of
this camps thing that we've already
talked about you know the echo chamber
and the creating of unification of you
know ideologically driven camps on
social media and on well on all
platforms really you know it's it's it's
really hard to avoid you know if you
watch a video on YouTube the
recommendations it comes up with will be
videos similar to the one that you just
watched you know what I mean it's it's
yeah it's really very anything's just
chosen if you you know look something up
and you've watched it and it's showing
you recommend all that looks interesting
it's bound to look interesting right
because you've been interested in the
first thing and before you know it
you're in this loop of watching thing
after thing after thing which is
actually all pretty closely related I
mean don't get me wrong I love YouTube
you can find anything you want on
YouTube tutorials information history
lessons whatever you want you know what
I mean but but it's very evil to avoid
the echo-chamber thing you know it's
very easy to get into a pattern where
you're basically just you know watching
things that confirm your assumptions
yeah instead of challenging those
assumptions you know yeah and this has
to be a feature of game B right is
regularly challenging your assumptions
you've got to got to got to be
comfortable with having shot assumptions
challenged or you're not fit to play
game B yeah well and so that when you
feel you're right cousin matter how many
people are telling you that's that's not
right if you honestly you know in the
face of having listened to all arguments
against and you see yes we will need to
stand your ground as well right people
tell you yeah and you know it seemed
like at some point they were getting
into this individual versus collective
thing which I mean I gotta say I have
you know I have real issues with that I
just can't figure out
you know let's say you know those who
want to call the individual you know the
proper unit of analysis or they want to
say that individual freedom is the most
important thing and trumps everything I
can certainly see a case to be made for
that you know but I can also see on the
other side it's like when you really get
down to it I mean you're not an
individual without you know something to
be compared to you or you know norms and
mores that are created together so it's
like it just can't be one or the other
no I think that's in terms of society in
terms of the social contract that's the
eternal right at the base of everything
else right underneath everything else
all of the other conflicts that's the
eternal question isn't it to what extent
is it acceptable to give up individual
self-determination to be part of a
cohesive smooth functioning society
because obviously no society functions
if everybody can do whatever the hell
they want wherever the hell they feel
like you know what I mean there then
there has to be some curtailing of that
in order for people to live together in
a mutually beneficial manner right so to
what extent is it acceptable to place
limitations on self-expression freedom
individual liberty whatever you want to
cry and I suppose like you know the
libertarian minded person would say well
they would come up with something like
the non-aggression principle or
something where you know as long as
you're not infringing on somebody else's
rights yeah but that's the conflicts
right between two people who want to do
something and by both of them wanting to
do it they're impinging on each other in
some way right it's not as clear-cut as
process I mean that's reasonable right
you need a conflict resolution process
which all parties buy into and are you
know have confidence in the in the in
the fairness of if you like right which
is what our legal system is supposed to
be is exactly that
flic resolution system which is as fair
as possible in principle I kind of like
the idea where you have laws written
down these are these are the guideline
principles right these are the basic
do's and don'ts of our society but we
understand that no written rule
universally applied can ever be fair or
just right there's always going to be
circumstances which in which you know
things become a good big ray which is
why you have jewelry's and so the the
written law is tempered with
understanding of the context and the
individual situation at a bit of
compassion and and and whatever right
and so that the principle of that I like
where it gets into problems in my
opinion is when judges are appointed
politically you know what I mean and
politics is driven by money and so
basically and the people with more money
can buy better lawyers and get better
legal interpretations and have better
ways of manipulating legal language to
fit their own ends and all of that kind
of thing that the spirit of honest
good-faith conflict resolution has now
become lost which is which is what it's
supposed to will be rooted in right
right well and I mean that's that that's
so what you're describing there is the
same thing that happened that happens
with central government for example
family no absolutely so I mean you know
so it's like hey who doesn't like the
idea of having interstate highways you
know that are maintained you know across
municipalities and states and all of
that but you know you get money involved
and then you get you know within then
you start talking about you know war and
you know the military-industrial complex
and all that stuff and it's like wait a
minute wait a minute wait a minute you
know so that's where you get into like
oh we really need some place to reboot
from well in my opinion game B doesn't
work while we have money cut profit
competitive advantage being sought III
don't see game B works under this I mean
one of the groups that I'm associated
with is the money free party and the
zeitgeist movement both of whom advocate
for resource-based economics which does
not involve the use of money right it's
more about game B would fit perfectly
into our views
I so love the conversations they're
having because you know resource-based
economic is all about that you have
individually empowered responsible for
themselves individuals choosing to
collaborate on that which matters to
them right so inefficient ways using
technology as it should you know as it
should be used if you know what I mean
everything possible and yeah sorry going
you were gonna say something well I mean
I'm just curious then since you've been
involved in there it's like well so
there's something like global commerce
just go away under that there are always
going to be certain things which exist
in some parts of the world and not in
other parts of the world you know I mean
raw materials for example which are
important for the manufacture of things
so no I mean I but I think it changes
its nature it no longer goes from you
know those with money can access it and
those without money card they're you
know a different decision-making process
is put into play I mean I I think a
great deal of scarcity that we seem to
endure under a monetary system is not
real scarcity right it's care staff oh
that goods remain high-priced and
therefore more profitable right and so
you know I really think not that I see a
clear pathway to get from a money ridden
well to a world without money because
it's a pretty big fucking step right I
mean just philosophically mentally
emotionally
it's a giant leap right but I do
honestly believe in my heart that money
fucks everything up not not the money
itself but the behavior that the money
brings out of people you know when you
have this thing this this magical thing
which can get you anything that you want
all of a sudden people will do things
for that which they would never
otherwise do you know what I mean it
just brings it and I'm not saying that
these tendencies existed all of us right
I really believe in that Solzhenitsyn
quote that the line between good and
evil does not run externally it runs
right through each and every individual
heart I really believe that but why it
creates systems which magnify and reward
the worst in our nature's you know I
mean it seems to me to be
a cataclysmically bad thing but but
that's what we've done so going back to
the original question about Commerce
yeah there would be exchanges of things
but in you know back in the original
ideas about in Smith you don't I mean
the original spirit of mutual mutual
benefit you know what I mean not one
exploiting the other not one profiting
at the expense of the other exchanges in
mutual interest so that's where we get
back to coherence and like I mean the
level of the level of trust that would
be required absolutely or something like
that to operate in the world is just a
long way away and I mean it gets
dismissed up results based economics
gets dismissed by people as oh it's just
Marxism riots just communism in another
form and in a way it is right because
everybody now has direct inputs into
what that which affects their lives you
know what I mean there's like rings
within rings within rings within rings
within rings of organisation because as
you quite rightly said we need to build
roads across countries right you know
you can't do that with a dozen people
you need to find ways of collaborating
and so you have you know the family unit
the the neighborhood unit the town unit
the city unit the county unit the city
and these things all overlay with each
other and are in cooperation with each
other of course all possible scales and
dimensions you know I mean it's it's
it's it's a magnificent and beautiful
thing and AI has there has the
capability of making sense of it all if
you know what I mean hmm you just threw
that in there huh well I don't I think
as soon as you put people in charge of
decision-making I I just think you're
asking for trouble do you know what I
mean III later there's you know
someone's doing someone a favor
someone's making a decision based on
less than the best possible of
information or whatever you know yeah
well it does seem to me like you know
capitalism did what it set out to do
which was essentially to you know create
innovation or whatever you want to call
but it's come to a point where like I
mean you know Jordan Peterson would even
admit this that you know all hierarchies
have a tendency to become top-heavy and
dis possess the vast majority at the
bottom yeah yeah and that's where we are
I think the primary hierarchies in which
all of the other cuz I I did a video
about this actually which was very
quickly I mean I think his basic point
about our hierarchies are not corrupt
you don't have bounds of plumbers you
know corrupt plumbers walking up and
down the street demand you cease their
services I think that's right broadly
speaking when you're just dealing with
people on a day to day basis I think
that's right you know I think it is
competence that is primarily what puts
people in their positions power in
communities and stuff yeah I on smaller
scales soon as you get into the really
big giant powerful hierarchies finance
governor and politics and so you know
media this kind of thing I think that's
not true I think these my rock is a
really really super corrupt you know
they've just had and I think it's just a
matter of time before that just happens
on its own I mean anytime you set up
hierarchies you know especially when
you're talking about power and resources
and you know competition and things I
mean it's just naturally gonna happen
especially when the individuals are so
disconnected you know and you don't you
don't feel like you have ownership in
the thing and so use you start to check
out anyway and then the people who have
the power they're the only ones that are
checked in because they're the only ones
that can make it do anything this whole
labor for money contract you know I mean
you're sound like a Marxist agrarian you
don't give a fuck about what you're
doing right you're not putting your
heart and soul into your into a job if
you're all you're getting is minimum
wage at the end of the week kind of
thing why do you give a fuck you're
doing as little as you can possibly get
away with and not get fired and still
get your ways check at the end of the
week you know and so yeah I don't know
what I wouldn't want to choose a number
I don't know what percentage of workers
work like that but I reckon it's pretty
high I reckon it's pretty high no I
would say it's pretty high even people
who like their jobs you know relatively
speaking like you don't I mean you're
still doing it
for a paycheck I mean like I like my
work you know but I don't I mean you
know if I didn't have to do it for a
paycheck I'd be doing something else man
yeah right I mean that that's really the
question isn't it if you didn't have to
earn a paycheck what would you be doing
with your time and I don't think there's
many people who can say I'd be doing
exactly what I'm doing now I'd be
fucking building furniture or something
you know
I mean honestly or something you know
I'd be doing something creative but not
you know writing computer code for some
multinational corporation you know yeah
and I mean you know with the best will
in the world good people all over the
place are part of the problem right I
mean you know with with good good people
just doing their thing just getting on
with their daily lives are contributing
to that which ultimately is oppressing
them and destroying their environment
right and I'm essentially because we
don't have any other choice I was having
a conversation with someone on online
the other day we're talking talking
about 10 years or so ago in the UK we
had the conservative liberal Alliance
right and the Liberals reneged on their
pledges about student fees and everybody
hated them so the next election
everybody voted against them and they
voted for the Tories who were you know
continual starett e-rate lower taxes for
the rich people but cut public services
blah blah blah blah blah you know but it
was just a reaction and to get something
different so they voted for their own
impoverishment you know what I mean
millions and millions and millions of
people voted for their own deep and
impoverishment right truck sorry Oh
I was just gonna say you do have to ask
the question what actual alternatives
are there when it comes to election time
you know what I mean right right well I
mean and so obviously at some point you
have to just say okay I got a you know
to work with what I've got you know I
think the challenge for people like us
is gonna be like okay and more more
probably the people who are leading the
charge say is like you know
the idea is at least what I get from
Brett Weinstein is like game B is
supposed to be able to out-compete game
a in some way have you picked up on that
at all it's about
I mean it's about complexity and he
draws a distinction between complex and
complicated complex being a mathematical
term yeah for a fundamentally
unpredictable system where you know tiny
changes in input leads a huge change
you'll feel familiar with the idea of
chaos and complex systems yes so that's
what he mean he's saying the game is
unable to cope with complexity because
it's systems of decision-making are
linear right they are saying I'm not
saying that's what you're saying that's
my take on what he's saying and the
right but what's it gonna take
complexity because it's a nonlinear
dynamic right and therefore it has the
capacity to cope with complexity so
what's it
a just totally fucking destroying
everything before game B Kenny you broke
up on me a little bit they gonna need to
repeat that well so my question then
would be what's it gonna take is it
gonna take
game age it's totally fucking destroying
everything before we get to the point
where game B looks good enough to
everybody enough people yeah I mean
that's a really good question it's a
question that I grappled with a lot but
one of the main drivers all the
resources of the above the
resource-based economics moment is a guy
called Jacque fresco he died a couple of
years ago the age of 102 or ever quite a
character anyway he is of the opinion
that until game a he didn't caught he
didn't conceptualize in that way he
didn't call it game a but same idea
until game a spectacularly fails and is
seen to fail and is known to be you know
unfit for purpose
only then will people seek the neces you
know the necessarily necessarily radical
solutions that are out there it feels
like we can't be terribly far from there
you know I mean it seemed like well I
just feels like we can't be terribly far
from that but you know who knows maybe
that's just the echo chamber that I'm
into right but yeah I tend to agree I
mean I but I don't see hahaha
I don't see us moving smoothly from game
a to game be I don't I don't see that
happening but they said something about
like in this video there's somewhere
where they make mention of the
transitional generations generations of
people ie centuries of time kind of
thing yeah I yeah a long yeah I don't I
don't see that no I see a much more if
game B is to is to take over from game a
I see a much more likely scenario being
the widespread collapse of game a very
large numbers of people you know wiped
out and from the ashes emerges okay
people playing game B I mean that's
that's all but you know it could just as
likely be small groups of people going
back to what's-his-name B groups dot
Dunbar Dunbar groups you know what I
mean they can dump the Dunbar
equilibrium that actually see yeah I
mean that would be that would be great I
mean you know but it's just like there's
so much it's so complicated right I mean
that's the problem right well because
that it's not it's not complex enough
it's too complicated the tendrils of
this months to reach into absolutely
everything it's everywhere it's in every
company it's in every school is in every
household it's Scott it's on every
screen you know what I mean it's it's in
every system in every city it's an ya
reaction you know what I mean it's it's
everywhere and so in a way I do think
the correct a level of attack or the
correct level of analysis is the
individual because only as individuals
do we have the ability to constrain evil
within our own hearts you know what I
mean and in our own actions only as
individual right but do we have the
power to do that right and Mike look at
Nazi Germany I guess right exactly so
it's individuals but then of course as
individuals as limits to what we can
actually accomplish in the world you
know what I mean and so it's it's a it's
a paradox in that sense on the one hand
change has to happen at the individual
level before it can happen at the growth
at the metal level you know at the multi
level but at the same time none of those
individual changes manifest in the world
at large really until enough people have
done it so that they can now collaborate
and and and and create physical changes
in the world
yeah and change systems and things like
that yeah it's almost like you need like
a you need an experimental space some
you know you need you need some
billionaire to buy an island and you
know try stuff out yeah a few thousand
people there and try stuff out and yeah
you know you put in but actually that
would be a that would be a great idea I
mean that really would be I love that
idea I'm not quite sure how you go about
actually doing it but I love that idea
I'm not you know I don't know anybody
capable of doing that reset and start
again any time the damage is always
contained it's not like you're risking
the entire global infrastructure on on
an untested idea you know what I mean
you can you can run it at least on a
small scale and of course there's always
going to be changes as you scale things
up but at least you can try on a medium
scale before going fright that's a great
idea
well I mean in the thing is the
challenge really is scalability yeah
because that's what I mean you know what
we've done is scaled I mean that's what
the broadcast model really did well was
scale and you know they were able to
control the message right because it was
only coming from a few trusted sources
yeah but that's just not the landscape
we're in anymore
no the source is the source is lost
there or
already he may or may not have been
people did trust and I mean listen I I
don't really know I was a kid or I or it
was before my time but you know the
walkers the Walter Cronkite's and the
Dan Rather of this world you know as I
understand it people really did trust
what they had to say and you know what's
his name Walter Cronkite stop the war
but stop the Vietnam War exactly I was
just gonna says something to that effect
so and III would I I think we are poorer
for not having those trusted voices that
you could rely on for at least as best
they knew it we're passing on truth to
you you know what I mean
and it's never truth it's always part of
the truth you know doing but at least
this part of it is true as best we know
and we haven't deliberately we haven't
deliberately you know what I mean
pushed it one way or the other to try
and create a perception in your mind you
know yeah yeah that's gone it's gone man
it's gone I mean I don't I can't think
of a single person or channel that I can
go to that I absolutely trust there's no
agenda there yeah right so that puts a
lot more of the you know the onus on you
as an individual to like whether you
want it or not or whether you even are
aware of that or not like there's a lot
more discernment that has to go on
because you can't just trust it no no
you really can't
you're on in Venezuela as an excellent
example I mean the the the primary
narrative about Venezuela is that Madero
is a dictator that he's impoverishing
his people that people are starving in
the streets that there's riots now I
hear from other sources and I have no
idea the truth where the truth lies in
this I'm absolutely no idea I don't know
any Venezuelans I don't have any
first-hand knowledge I've never been
there you know what I mean so I'm
talking from no but I know other sources
sources which I basically trust although
I don't trust anyone completely but that
I basically trusted are saying no that
the u.s. is waging an economic war on
Madero and this is why they don't have
food
there because you know supply lines have
been cut this sanctions there's and and
so on and so on but Madero is actually
Madeira I'm slightly getting his name
wrong it's something like that I'm
slightly getting his name of it anyway
but his he was elected by whatever
eighty percent of the people that the
people are you know squarely behind him
for the most part that the
anti-government protests are small
numbers of people financed by the CIA
blah blah blah blah now you couldn't
have two more different stories here
right where's the truth and as an
outside observer where can I go to
someone who will tell me what's actually
happening there which of these version
of events is closer to the truth where
do I go for that yeah I mean there's no
way and I don't know the the I mean I
don't even know that under the old model
there was anywhere you know because at
some point it just becomes like too far
removed from where you are to have any
accurate picture from anybody you know
but yeah it's frustrating because you
want to have an accurate understanding
of what's going on but at the same time
it's like it's impossible so you have to
assume that there is probably some bit
of truth on both sides of that equation
yeah I mean it goes back to what you're
saying right at the very very start
about the space between yes and no right
it's about holding all of that stuff in
your head at the same time and not
settling on any of it right holding all
of it lightly you know there's probably
some truth mixed up in all of it I don't
know what it is and until more
information comes along I'm just gonna
have to hold the uncertainty right yep
and you have to be comfortable with that
Ryan so that goes back to patience and
humility that you know was in this video
and the the idea that you know there was
this other idea that so we were taught
we were talking earlier about you know
when the resonance happens you know how
how do you maintain it or what do you do
with it and like what you know
greenhalgh makes this thing about you
know you'll so you have the significant
breakthrough and it happens and
everybody recognizes it
and then what we do is that we are way
too quick to take that as being the
breakthrough yeah as opposed to saying
okay we had that and now that starts a
process you know a new process of
understanding and assimilating that
breakthrough and embodying that and you
know looking for the next one instead of
taking it as the thing and so again
that's about patience and about being
able to hold on to two apparently
mutually exclusive ideas you know let me
ask you something I mean the three of
them Daniel Jamie and Jordan and the two
of us broadly in this conversation we
talked about game being quite nebulous
esoteric kind of terms right and
necessarily so to a certain degree right
but in terms of its utility what am I
trying to say here there needs to be an
interface between the non-semantic world
of game B and the literal semantic world
that we inhabit most of the time right
because I mean I don't see us living
permanently in that game B space right
you know yet we enter into it and as we
become more practice we do so in a
deliberate way right
presumably to fulfill a particular need
a particular function or just to
maintain a sense of cohesion and and and
you know unity and and whatever in there
in the group but there needs to be some
sort of interface right between if you
like the real world and the and the and
the special world that game be in
inhabits you know does that make sense
yeah it does I mean you know what I the
thing that I mean that's the thing I
always come back to you know when I'm
thinking about this stuff is it's like
okay what is it that's gonna allow these
two things to co-exist for a sir
period of time yeah because it's not
gonna be I mean unless it's the
catastrophic scenario where game a
catastrophic Li fails and a whole bunch
of people fuckin you know mass
casualties and you know it's hell on
earth for a while you know there's gonna
have to be a period of time when game B
exists alongside game a in order to
essentially out-compete it at some point
yeah and I don't know what that looks
like exactly well is the end goal to be
game being all the time so whether
you're with one person or whether you're
you know you know in a theater with 200
others that you you're in a constant
state of connection and coherence I mean
as well I mean I do think a certain
degree of coherence you know can be
maintained you know this idea of global
consciousness and the third rising you
know and and always being in this I
don't know I mean that sounds to me like
an eight well it sounds like to me like
a state that just doesn't it shouldn't
be maintained in a sense you know it
should be sort of like you go there and
you know then you come back and
reassemble whatever you need to
reassemble in order to actually act in
the world
in that sense yeah I mean that could be
game a thinking in that you need the
assimilation sign that you know if
you're in the assimilation happens in
real time as you go kind of thing maybe
when you're playing game be fully and
you're fully immersed in it and you're
all practiced that's it you know maybe
maybe that retreating retreating for
assimilation maybe maybe that becomes
not necessary it happens as you go maybe
well yeah it could you know but it's
again it goes back to what you were
saying about you know Jordan's line
about the you know the words as pointers
you know and and what I'm really trying
to do when we talk is I'm really trying
to evoke in you you know a certain kind
of felt experience you know yeah
and so in that way I think you could I
think you could maintain that you know
and be aware of that more often than not
you know it's the romantic idea isn't it
to be level with people all the time you
know what I mean yeah yeah but the
problem is really it's the sort of thing
you do with your lover you know what I
mean that's the kind of communication
you have with your lover maybe with your
children you know the name but is it
kind of level of closeness and intimacy
I mean that would be a beautiful thing
to have at large in the world that would
be fucking yeah so I mean but there it
is right the level of trust that's
involved in that is massive yeah you
know and the fact that you know the idea
that you could be out there trying to
play that game and that not everybody
else is really interested in playing
that game yeah that's hard that's yeah
quite brutally in fact really to think
that you're gonna make yourself that
vulnerable you know without being a
hundred percent sure that it's gonna
work out for you is well if you're on a
show then you don't make you cellphone
that's fair but I mean to me I think
what I would hope comes out of this
would be to develop some real specific
strategies to create institutions that
are more game be oriented yeah in the
guilt trip a couple of very good points
I think which would be helpful I think
perhaps at least in the transition
towards game be if not in full-on game
be be a redundant in full-on game be you
may to suggest you saying in debate when
people are debating with each other when
one person has made their argument
before the responder makes their
argument they first summarize
respectfully the argument that they've
just heard right and I think that's I
think that's a fantastic starting point
just for a start you much less likely to
respond
angrily if your first having to take
that time to do that right and you're
happy to consider properly what they're
saying I think it's I think it's a
lovely idea
he may not ride it well and that goes to
what we were saying earlier to about
making sure that we're operating with
the same definitions and yeah absolutely
absolutely absolutely yes it's all set
out and he made another point as well I
can't think what it was no it was a long
similar lines but also I think important
important to game be yeah so there's a
well so right so there's there's
actually like there's two domains or
levels you know on which we're talking
about here because you know on that
level that's like an interpersonal level
where I'm learning new ways to interact
and to you know be with other people
right yeah and there's and then there's
there's I just think there's gonna have
to be some kind of institutional you
know level as well like I mean I just
don't see it happening in and of itself
you know in groups of people like this I
don't know and maybe I'm wrong I know
you mean but I also I also feel equally
that it can't possibly happen top-down
from the institutional level either I
mean there's no impetus for them to do
that there's no no I understand that
well but the idea would be that if you
know if we were to you know somehow
change our politics in such a way that
like let's say for example well let's
say for example something as simple as
you know you want to start a company
okay you've got an idea you're gonna
make some widgets and every and and so
you then you're gonna incorporate right
and so at that point what if the
government says okay we're gonna
actually incentivize you turning this
corporation into something like a
cooperative
right and so in some way we provide an
incentive to you as a you know
entrepreneur or whatever you want to
call yourself we provide you an
incentive that makes it more attractive
for you to create a co-op than to create
a corporation and that's great and this
kind of thing is fantastic but how do we
get governments to start implementing
policies along those lines I mean I mean
no electron sander I don't know not that
it couldn't because his loads of ideas
like that which would absolutely be
steps on the road to a but I don't see
any way of leveraging pressure on our
elected officials given that they've
been bought and paid for a long time ago
I mean I think most people understand
this now this is no longer conspiracy
theory right most people absolutely
accept this as a fact of nature now but
lobbyists and campaign and campaign
contributors essentially control
political agendas right yep so yeah I
don't see until legislation like
citizens united and Buckley versus Valeo
and I mean so this kind of stuff is
repealed and you know corporate and and
wealthy interests are no longer allowed
to find companies I mean for fuck's sake
they spent over a billion dollars on the
last presidential campaign a billion
dollars it's just nuts it's absolutely
fucking nuts it's an advertising and
marketing campaign how is that got
anything to do with you know sensible
policies by which the road by which to
run a country you know it's got the two
things are no longer even pretending to
be connected to each other anymore
they're not even pretend me Congress no
longer really even there's not even
pretending to write there they don't
pretend to represent their constituents
for the most part I mean there are a
couple of exceptions right but for the
most part congressmen and Senators well
yeah well let me but so so here's where
I would maybe I mean I'm you know again
it remains to be seen where this goes
but you know in the States we have a
real you know there's a lot of energy
around you know the candidacy say of
Bernie Sanders and
the fact that the Energy's there is just
encouraging to me now
whether or not you know he he gets the
nomination or he wins the presidency or
even if he wins whether or not he's able
to you know do anything it's like here
is at least a person who has been
staunch in his you know disdain for
money and politics and you know
top-heavy whatever whatever you know for
decades you know has not just come to
this you know these positions for the
sake of political expediency you know
when he started talking about these
things right yeah so this is a really
bad word in the u.s. I don't really
understand why I know it's crazy but I
tell you what excites me even more than
Bernie Sanders because he's what he's 78
or something yeah he's an old guy he's
an old guy I mean not that I've got
anything against old per se but there
comes a time when you know your job it's
a big job anyway whatever that's one
side what excites me more in American
politics at the moment I talked about it
a bit on the discord was that Alexandria
or Cassio Cortes and and that whole
movement of grassroots support not using
huge amounts of money yeah they collect
contributions but it's mostly about
grassroots action and knocking on doors
and having little meetings in town
centers and balls and that kind of thing
you know what I mean and this is this is
where I think real change can come from
is if a movement like that can snowball
but once it does snowball it becomes
victim I reckon to all the same power
dynamics that the existing power so
there it is right but that that's where
that's where maybe game B can really
play a role right because if we can you
know if if we can manage to call that
what it is when we see it happening now
again you're right the thing has a power
and an inertia of its own you know and
the military-industrial complex is not
going to go away
without fight for sure it's gonna
they've got all the guns right exactly a
lot of pain and suffering behind if it
goes away you know but it's like we've
you know we've all got to be able to
work together to call out the bullshit
and so if it ends up that you know
people get corrupted again I mean that's
why there is legislation you know to get
money out of politics for the most part
or in in a pretty significant way but
you know you just you can't get anything
done that's right and even even the
House of Representatives as a whole has
some legislation on the table but they
can't they won't be able to get it
through the Senate you know and so it
doesn't really matter at this point
yeah and they certainly won't get it
boss the president right so I don't know
it'll be interesting to watch but it is
it's frustrating you know as a like as a
parent of a ten year old you know it's
really sometimes just depressing to
think that we're gonna have to you know
live through
couple generations of like chaos in
order to get to the other side so I'm
interested in what you were saying about
somehow or other getting game be
incorporated into say for example what
are they called again the citizens you
know they're not citizens united what
are they called again this so jump it's
Democrats so it was justice Democrats
House Democrats yes so you know let's
say this justice Democrats movement
let's say that you know Jordan and Jamie
and Daniel could get in there and start
talking to these guys and you know
getting them involved in sessions you
know trying to achieve coherence or at
least getting the principles of what
coherence is all about across to them
and and so on I like that idea talk more
I like that idea has evolved in these
movements yeah I I don't know you know
that's that's on a level of you know
organization that I have no access to
you I guess you know it would take some
you know it would takes getting involved
with you know say the rebel wisdom guys
or somebody who has access to those
people you know context man I mean
Jamie's worked with some pretty
highfalutin people well I mean he's you
know he obviously went to you know these
conferences in an attempt to you know
solve things like global war you know
see something about the oceans right
there was something he was involved in
and he said he got down there and the
thing got derailed by you know somebody
getting triggered over right there sir
or gender or something you know mr. fry
man then your own personal you know
misgivings oh yeah so obviously when you
get these people into those places it
doesn't always go well to do so people
out there can you actually have a
sensible discussion about climate change
or gender politics or politics of any
kind actually come to that without it
likely becoming bitter and I mean
there's just so few people
that aren't ideologically and
emotionally invested in something in
something or rather to something with
this with this identity politics and
yeah but you know I think it's less I
think identity politics is just kind of
a symptom of you know a deeper problem
which is like I feel so disconnected to
you know the world and to humanity it's
like that's why I think you know stuff
like Buddhism and you know that sort of
training exposure to that is so
important to me because it's like
without having some sense that like we
are all one yeah you know what I mean
yeah like how you you know that is so
fundamental to everything that I do is
this constant you know returning to that
insight and it just but as you go about
doing that what what happened what
practices do you do to return to that
insight oh well I mean it's a lot of
like you did you were you showing me
that there's that Jamie wheel video
about something about coherence but I'm
super excited about his new book that
he's working on right because he's
talking about these kinds of things and
he's talking about storming like breath
is the the primary to me you know breath
work being able to sit and do I mean
something like Vipassana meditation is I
mean like you get to a point where it's
not like you're having some kind of I
don't know it just you you get to a
point where there's enough stillness
that you know divisions start to fall
away and you know you're you're actually
physiologically changing you know how
reactive you are to things and how
personally you take the
and you know and then I mean a lot of it
just comes down to you know having done
that work for a long time you just sort
of start to internalize it you know you
were talking about what happens when you
try to seek coherence more and more
often it doesn't become easier and again
like I don't know that it comes becomes
easier but I think you get better at it
and you have more direct access to it
but I mean that like everything you know
I started looking at Buddhism when I was
like in high school you know when I
first started coming out of you know
kind of the rote Christian tradition
that I was raised in you know in high
school I started asking questions and
stuff and you know started looking at
Zen and Taoism and stuff like that and I
mean I just think that stuff is it's
critical to understanding that you know
we're all in this together kind of and I
mean I you can get to it other ways I
mean I heard they were talking about how
it's like oh you know a lot of times
astronauts have a similar yeah yeah
orientation yeah you know because it's
just when you get to that place and you
actually look back it's like you can't
see it any other way anymore
you know and so I all those lines you
have in your head are going yeah all
right they're all arbitrary in there
yeah yeah yeah it must be it must be a
pretty profound experience it really
must yeah I mean so to me it's like you
know there's got to be I mean you're
you're just you know and then it goes
back to what we were talking about with
trying to integrate the game be stuff
somehow and it seems like that's still
really difficult to do because people
just aren't on that page you know but
you would think that these justice
Democrat types would be amenable to that
is that right I mean yeah I have to say
she's a very impressive young woman I
watched a little watched a couple of
hours of her campaign speeches and just
talking to people and and interviews and
so on and she's she's pretty impressive
she's very young and she's in certain
ways rough around the edges but I find
that quite
earing personally it scene you know she
seems genuine doesn't seem like she's
thinking too hard about her answers
she's just answering she's saying what
she thinks you know what I mean and
that's very refreshing in politics I was
talking to someone about this the other
day Teresa may is the Prime Minister in
the UK you probably know that when she's
asked a question in an interview that is
off script you don't mean that she
wasn't doesn't have a ready answer for
you can it's not just her you can see
with all the politicians they you can
see the wheels turning as they run
potential answers through their head and
think what are the ramifications of
their ads that make me look at what's a
person gonna think about blah blah blah
blah blah they can no longer I don't
think they're even capable anymore of
simply saying what they think you know
what I mean they're so entrenched in
this gotta weigh up all of this and this
and these interests and these interests
and can't upset these people and can't
upset these people these people vote for
me if I say this and blah blah blah blah
blah all of that consideration is it has
to go into every single thing that they
say on camera yeah I mean that's kind of
just a product of the system to you I
mean like you know it's I mean it's all
now just basically a marketing yeah yeah
yeah might as well be hamburgers versus
pizza right what do you want for dinner
right same thing and all the people that
want hamburgers you fucking pizza
reaches your idiot all right well listen
Eric I I'm gonna I'm gonna get off man
so I can get on to other things but I
appreciate you you know yeah they can
this is good yeah it was great I
listened apart from anything else I
really enjoyed the conversation yeah I
mean I'm not sure how much if any
headway we made but hey listeners it was
it was a really enjoyable conversation
yeah for sure and I mean it's just
what's that did we achieve coherence or
well yeah I mean I would say that we
were able to you know now did we come up
with some you know new was there an and
mergence I'm not sure but I mean I can
guarantee that yeah we definitely were
able to kind of hold things hold two
things together and and work together to
try and locate the signal amongst the
noise which i think is what it's really
all the one original thought I had or at
least it felt original I don't recall
having heard it already anywhere else
although I may have done you know what I
mean was the thing about technology
supporting the biological organism up
until recently that's that that's that's
something I think perhaps I might never
have come up with had it not been in the
context of the conversation and you know
the the relationship between what we
were saying to each other it's possible
it's possible it emerged that it's also
possible to version something I did see
or read and don't remember seeing or
reading it so that's equally possible
right but at least at least it plucks it
out yeah yeah and so what we should do
like I mean this would be cool to do
this you know again sometime so we'll
just well we'll keep it open but I mean
you know we can always direct message on
the discord or whatever yeah absolutely
and you know I'm just what I'm mostly
interested in is like okay like I get it
you know and I'm on board you know like
so what are where's the you know where's
the organizational movement yeah yeah
well I it's like just going to a retreat
you know or going to a workshop or
something but I mean like how does game
B get inside and infiltrate you know
game a yeah the people I know and I mean
I don't have a wide circle of friends
but you know there are maybe there's one
possibly two people that I could have
this conversation with among the people
that I know do you know I mean yeah I
nobody else I know it's so far away from
you know there's so much they would need
to learn and understand before we could
even start having this kind of a
conversation you know yes that's right
that is true so I mean like that so that
knows you
I don't I don't I I don't see much
preparedness for game B I really don't
right you know that's that's I think
you're right I mean that tells you that
you know there's a there's a long way to
go and we're definitely in the minority
[Laughter]
minority yeah well I'm gonna I'm a sign
off man so again thanks for the
conversation and yeah pleasure pleasure
did you get a recording of this did you
read did you choose to record do you
know I didn't get one so if you
automatically at my own because I'm the
initiator cervical is automatically at
my own yeah I mean it might be you know
worth taking another listen you know
like you said I'm not sure what well I
think good stuff in there and I mean
listen I've got a channel anyway I'm
gonna stick it up there anyway if you
don't watch you just stick it up because
I mean see you know here's the other
piece of it right is like at the very
least even if it's boring as hell the
you know 90% of anybody who would watch
it it's it's it is modeling the
conversation you know I'm just gonna put
it up unedited I'm just going to put it
up as is I mean I I think if you edit it
you could potentially lose something
right I mean I know it's to almost 2
hours long and people don't sit and
watch two hours of just two guys talking
to each other right but I'm inclined to
leave it unedited and I mean I could
always take some snippets out of it
later for whatever reason but yeah I
mean quiet just leave it in its I think
that's perfectly fine with me yeah all
right good good it's a lot less work for
me that way as well right okay Philip
pleasure man all right Cheers take it
easy speak soon bye bye